Hello hello hello again! I'm Caner, I am with you with another video guys.
Today we are going to talk about the pilot assessments. Yeah, I've been getting lots of questions.
Today we're going to record the generic one. The generic one will be about general information about how you should prepare for an interview.
I'll give details, I'll give some hints. You have to follow that. Then you can apply all the information that you will get from this video to any airlines.
So what I mean is going to be very generic. You need to do some specific researches about the airline that you will apply for.
Apart from that, I will record a separate video about how you should prepare for Emirates Airline pilot interview process individually.
That being said, let's continue with the pilot assessments video. First of all, you need to know your application requirements by heart.
This is the most important thing. If you want to give them a good impression, please apply when you have the requirements.
I've seen lots of guys, and also they're asking me, 'Oh I don't have ATPL, can I apply for the job?'
'I don't have a green card, can I apply for a job in the US?' 'I don't have CPL or 500 hours yet, can I apply for it?'
The first and simple answer is: No. You can send a text message, an email, whatever the thing, then you can explain your situation individually.
But please do not apply to any job without meeting their application criteria, because when you apply and you've been rejected,
The next time, maybe you can get some penalties. For instance, if you cannot be selected, if your application is not accepted,
There might be some penalties for that. Please don't put yourself in that situation so that in the future when you meet the criteria,
You will be judged based on your first application. This is really important. I'm saying that, you can think this is very dumb to apply for a job that you don't meet the criteria,
But there are hundreds of pilots applying those jobs without meeting all the criteria for this job. Believe me, I got lots of questions.
Second thing I would like to mention is timing. Timing is everything. Okay, you have the requirements, you have the qualifications,
You can apply for any job, and then do you think it is the best time to apply? You should ask this question to yourself.
I'll give from my own personal experience. When I applied for the job for Emirates, Emirates were hiring a lot.
They were even hiring pilots from turboprop because all market, I mean the aviation market in the world were hiring.
So they had to reduce their requirements. They need more pilots, but there is not much pilot around, so they reduce the requirements.
And if they have lots of pilots available to them, or they can get wide-body first officers from another companies like nowadays,
Let's say from Cathay or other companies, they increase this leverage so that you literally cannot apply.
That being said, when I applied Emirates, Emirates were hiring lots of pilots and that's why they put the leverage down.
Meanwhile I begged all of my pilot friends at Turkish Airlines: 'Let's apply, let's apply!' And they were in Triple Seven, they were having a great lifestyle there.
And they didn't think much. And then they didn't apply. I was 100% sure if I was selected, they would be selected as well.
Because we got same assessment process with Turkish Airlines, and Turkish Airlines assessment process is way more difficult than the Emirates selection process.
Because that was the first time as a cadet and there was high competition in that. And none of my friends applied. And COVID happened.
Because of the COVID, they didn't like the job that they are doing, they wanted to come to Emirates. After COVID, Emirates opened the job applications.
But what do you think? Do you really think that when they open the new job openings, they will hire the same amount as my time? Of course not.
During my time they were hiring hundreds, but right now they will hire only three or four pilots. So do you think it is possible for you to make it?
What's the likelihood of getting positive news? Of course, very little. And guess what happened? None of them could make it, except one.
But I was 100% sure if those guys applied like three years ago, they would make it. So timing is everything.
You should analyze the market. What do they need? Where should I start? Which job gives me better opportunity to apply?
Should I wait for it? Should I apply for that? And I cannot give you direct information about it, you should analyze the market needs.
Rather than wasting your time to go to that level of job, you should initially choose this job to gain some airline experience.
Maybe from this job, maybe turboprop, then you can go for jet like Airbus or Boeing. This is always what I recommend to new pilots.
Don't focus on your ultimate goal when you don't have the criteria. You should think for the next step. Don't think for the six or seven steps ahead.
They will make you fall down from this path. Please focus on your next step. This is really important.
You meet the criteria, you think it's a perfect time, now go for it! Apply! Don't forget, this is going to be the first place where you are going to shine.
Make an amazing application. Don't feel anything wrong, just check each individual column that you need to fill.
And pay particular attention to fill all these forms correctly. Don't get any emails from company's HR stating you didn't complete this part.
'Your signature is missing there.' You should do this, you should do that, because it's not nice. You should do everything at once.
And then prepare an amazing CV or resume. Also don't forget to get amazing recommendation letters beforehand.
Your recommendation letters are really important, and I must say that in the US they literally pay particular attention about the recommendation.
If you have a couple of years to apply for your dream job, pay particular attention for your education level as well.
Though it is not a mandatory requirement for having a university degree, I strongly recommend you to have a university degree.
They simply put you ahead, especially in the US. Your application is the first place where you are going to shine. They will check each detail.
For that reason, don't make any mistake. Don't skip anything. Don't think that this is not important.
If the job is asking, 'where did you fly?', if you flew 300 different destinations, list them, 300 of them. Don't think 'it's not important'.
You never know what is important for a recruiter or not. Give as much detail as possible, but please don't repeat yourself.
Or don't give extra information they don't need. For instance, if they don't need your high school diploma, send the highest level degree.
And if you had a master's, you don't need to send your primary school high school diplomas. Don't do this. Lots of people are doing it.
Please read the requirements and send whatever is needed. Exactly. Full stop. Start preparation for the interview.
Yes guys, for instance for Emirates, I used latestpilotjobs.com. You have to pay for it, but it was really good tool.
I was joining Emirates Airline, it was a great tool. I was able to see other pilots' candidates' experiences, what did they do, what questions did they get.
And you get a really really detailed knowledge about the interview process line by line. This is a really good tool, use it.
For instance, I can give you another tool for US airlines, you can go that page: aviationinterviews.com.
Again, you need to pay for it, but definitely it is worth every single penny that you spend for it. I took lots of beneficial information.
They give you each single step that you need to know. And from my personal US experiences, I got exactly the same questions and preparation steps.
They are not hidden. Those companies will send you the interview steps as well, but they're not going to send you how you need to prepare.
So those websites are really good tools for you to get ready for your interview selection process. Don't skip.
The next thing, you have to refer back your pilot career. Because in each airline, I guarantee you, they will ask you certain sets of questions.
They are there in the aviation industry for a long time and you will be getting it. I'm 100% sure. What are these questions?
'What would you do if...?' and 'Tell me about a time when...'. This is two sets of aviation questions that you will get it.
In order to answer those questions, you need to have some memory refreshments. Go back and check each detail.
And prepare professionally about these questions. Those previous websites I just told you, there are tons of questions and answers about that.
I'll give you an example. 'Tell me about a time when you had a disagreement with a captain'. Okay? This time, they don't particularly look for a certain answer.
They are looking for how methodological your thinking process is. So you should be very professional, don't make any silly jokes.
And don't give very stupid examples on that. They don't ask you to give very complicated examples. They are not requiring you to answer in a certain way.
You should give very simple solution. For instance, disagreement with captain: 'It was 7 degrees, it was wet, I wanted to put engine anti-ice on, and captain said no need for that'.
'And I said it's requirement by supplementary procedure in FCOM, we have to do it'. That's it. No need to give complicated example.
Please before going an interview, review all your memories. Try to answer all of these questions on your own and just review your interview process.
Next step is purely optional, you don't have to do it. It's an interview prep. This is very common thing in the US.
You can have a simulation of an interview. You can find interview companies, they can literally simulate all these interviews.
They keep asking questions, they comment about your answers, how you should answer. Then they will listen you, they are professional.
They are most of the time are hiring managers of pilot recruitment departments. Did I do it? Yes. Did I get benefit? I totally get it.
It helped me to relax, and I knew where I am on the track, so I knew my weaknesses. It's purely optional, but I would recommend a lot.
Now, it is time for the interview day. It is time for you to shine. Don't forget: first impressions are the most important thing.
Have a nice briefcase with you, have a perfect suit, make a perfect haircut. Especially if you are a female, have a decent clothing as well.
Believe me, it doesn't work in the real life if you think they should interview me for who I am, not how I look like. First impression is scientifically proven.
You should be going there to show you like: I am a professional. I want to be a first officer or a captain in your company.
And you should be telling this with your body language. You should be having self-trust and you should look perfectly.
Don't forget you've been interviewed the moment that you step in the facilities. Your interview starts at the airport.
When you board their airplane, be careful about what you are saying. When you are staying in the hotel, be professional in the hotel.
Don't do anything stupid that's gonna cost you a job. I had some examples like this, people start drinking a lot, and they've been reported.
Don't risk your multi-million US dollar career because of these stupid things. Be a social guy, don't go to the corner be silent.
Try to socialize with the people, communicate with them. How you communicate as a group, these things are really important for recruiters.
And one common mistake: please don't forget if you are invited as a group, they are not your competitors.
There are some jobs, 20 guys are invited and 20 of them are selected. Sometimes none of them are selected. So you need to collaborate.
Interview, don't take anything personal. They will have poker face there. Recruiters are not allowed to tell you anything like 'Oh that's great, we will hire you'.
Go there, be professional, stay away from making silly jokes, be yourself, be relaxed, calm. Answer the questions and finish it.
About the simulators: they want to see your pilot skills, how you are communicating. CRM, CRM and CRM. CRM is the number one tool they check.
Don't focus on your landings. Most probably they won't check your landings if it's a new type. Focus on teamwork, management of non-normals.
Make yourself calm down. Repeat it 100 times beforehand. Just try to find a solution for yourself to keep yourself calm.
Once you are done, show you're confident and don't forget to thank them. They already spent lots of money for you for the interview process.
Thank you for giving this opportunity. That concludes how you should prepare for a pilot interview. If you follow this formula, you will get a job.
If you want to have a professional help, you can contact with me via my email, my YouTube, my Instagram. Thank you so much for watching!